Let's talk about binary search tree operations.
There are three basic operations that you can't perform on a binary search, tree search operation,
insert operation and deletion operation.
Let's start by learning about the search operation.
The algorithm depends on the property of binary search, a tree that if each left some tree has values
below the root and each writes up tree has values above the root.
This is the the basics of the BSD that we have learned that the left tree is less that it values is
less than the root value, and the rights of tree is greater than the root value.
For example, if you are searching for a number four in this city, and by the way, this is BSD, because
if we check, as I told you, I draw a line from here, all these value on the left should be less than
eight and all of these values.
To that, I should be greater than eight.
OK, now let's see how we could search of how the search operation works and we ask this.
We start passing the route, so it has been added to the stack.
We go to three.
So three has been added to the stack.
We go six, because we are searching for three four, which is greater than three.
So again, let me show you how it works.
Eight.
We are searching for four for less than eight.
Yes, so go left three.
Now, the route for is greater than or less than three, it is greater than three.
So go right, we approach six for less than six or greater than six.
So it is less than six go to that left.
We go to the left until reaching for.
This is the search operation that we are going to implement in BSD coding in C and Java.
Let's learn about the insert operation.
Inserting a value in the correct position is similar to searching because we try to maintain the ruled
that the left tree is less as lesser than the root, and the rights of tree is larger than that.
We keep going either right sub tree or left tree, depending on the value, and we reach a point.
And when we reach a point left or right sub three is now we put the new node there.
OK.
This is the insert algorithm.
Let's start by maintaining this example.
We need to insert number four in the three.
OK, so we start with eight.
Four is less than eight or greater than eight.
It is less than eight.
So we go to the left.
We reach a sub note that it is a route for a sub tree.
It is value is three.
For it's less than three or greater than three, it is greater than three, so I will go right from
three I reach six six is a new route for another three four.
We are going to insert it is less than six or greater than six.
It is less than six, but we reached a null value to the left.
OK, this is the trick.
So we reach a null value to the left.
We insert it.
So we insert the value of this number or this note that we are going to insert OK when reaching a null
value.
We insert OK.
We are going to see all of these in fully detailed example in the next videos, implementing them in
C and Java.
Now, let's learn about the deletion operation.
There are three cases for deleting a node from the binary search tree.
Case one in the first case, the note to be deleted is a leaf note in such a case, simply delete the
note from the tree.
We are going to delete number four.
This is a three BSD.
We are going to delete number four, so we have search for the four and we are going to delete it,
executing a deletion here.
It's very simple because we didn't change any old.
So we delete it.
And this is the final BSD.
OK.
We didn't move anything, we didn't change any order.
And everything works fine.
Let's see that the Legion operation in the case number two, they're not to be deleted.
Lies has a single child, not in such a case.
Follow the steps below Replace that note with its child note and remove the child node from its original
original position.
Let's take an example.
Here we need to delete number six.
Six has a sibling, has a child, which is seven.
And if we delete number six, like in the first case, it would be detached and we have removed all
seven.
So what is the solution?
We replaced the note with its child note like this, but things happen and.
Removing it so we have replaced.
We have removed six, we have replaced it by seven.
Move it up, and we have.
The final note.
Is seven is they're placed under three?
OK.
It's a very simple.
Now, there is a third case here that we are going to delete that note to be deleted has two children.
OK.
We have seen that the deletion operation of a note that does not does not have any children is very
simple.
Simple, we delete the note if a note in the second case contained only one child, so we replace it
child with it.
The third case is the most complex one and the third case that note to be deleted has two children.
It's in such case.
Follow the steps below.
Get the inorder successor of the note this is that three replaced the note with the inorder successor
and remove the in order successor from its position.
How to do that?
This is the example we are going to remove.
Number three.
We're going to delete it, we replaced the note with inorder successor.
What is the in order successor of three?
It is four and remove the in order successor from its original position.
So we remove four and replace it three and now.
It is replaced here.
So Ford is replacing the city.
It's very simple.
See you guys.
We start by detecting that note that we are going to delete.
We get the in order successor of the note.
So if we are making a note, three of of characters like B, the E, so that successor of E is F.
So the following of this component or this note in that order that we have replaced the three is the
successor we replaced the second step, replaced the note with the inorder successor.
We replace the three was it's an order successor, which is Ford.
And we removed the in order successor from its original position.
This is what we are going to implement in the next videos.
How to implement this binary search tree and how to work with that with.